Ernest L. Hartmann Papers MS211
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Ernest L. Hartmann Papers
1900 -- 2014
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Hartmann, Ernest L.
Hartmann, Dora, 1902-1974
Hartmann, Heinz
MS211
103.2 Linear Feet
6 Digital Object(s)
2 Web sites
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Arrangement
This collection was organized preliminarily into nine series during rehousing; final series arrangement will be decided during future processing. Material related to Heinz and Dora Hartmann is separated out into Series 2; however their correspondence and photographs are also to be found in other series, e.g. Series I, VI, and VIII. Series I: Personal papers consists mainly of correspondence, photographs, ephemera, official documents and certifications, and personal writings, arranged in three parts: alphabetically filed ephemera, official documents, photographs, and personal and professional correspondence; personal correspondence; and personal dream logs. Series II: Heinz and Dora Hartmann and family papers consists of their personal and professional correspondence, manuscripts and publications, notes, artwork, legal documents, minutes, and memoranda, arranged in rough chronological order. Series III: Professional correspondence and professional associations consists of minutes, brochures, papers, journals, and correspondence and is grouped into three rough categories: professional correspondence, Association for the Study of Dreaming (ASD) materials, and other professional organization materials. Series IV: Scientific publications and drafts contains drafts, prints, and reprints of articles with associated correspondence and data and is arranged in chronological order. Series V: Research data and materials contains research, datasets, study subject files, grant materials, correspondence, and PhD dissertations. Material in this series is arranged roughly by study, and studies are arranged in rough chronological order. Series VI: Early 20th century Austrian and German psychoanalytic literature and other books contains journals and books of Heinz, Dora, and Ludo Moritz Hartmann (Heinz Hartmann's father) dating mostly from the 1920s to 1930s. The series has been arranged chronologically within journal title but otherwise is not arranged. Series VII: Employment files contains official documents and certifications, awards, booklets, and photographs and is not arranged. Series VIII: Unsorted boxes contains ephemera, official documents and certifications, research, data, publications and manuscripts, photographs, and correspondence and is not arranged. Series IX: Audio tapes contains audiotapes in albums and is not arranged.
Biographical / Historical
Ernest (Ernst) Louis Hartmann was born in Vienna, Austria, on February 25, 1934. He was the elder of two sons born to Dora Karplus Hartmann and Heinz Hartmann; their younger son, Lawrence (Lorenz) Hartmann, also went on to become a distinguished psychiatrist.
Heinz Hartmann was a prominent psychoanalyst, a favorite student and collaborator of Sigmund Freud. Dora Karplus Hartmann was a pediatrician, psychiatrist, psychoanalyst, and mountaineer. The family emigrated from Austria in 1938 due to the rise of Nazism, first to France and Switzerland, then to New York City in 1941. There, Ernest Hartmann attended the Fieldston School, the University of Chicago (from which he graduated in 1952 after only one year of study), and Yale University School of Medicine, where he received his M.D. in 1958. His career at Tufts Medical School began as assistant clinical professor of psychiatry, 1964-1966, then assistant professor of psychiatry, 1966-1969, until Hartmann became a full professor in 1975, one of only three full professors at the School of Medicine at the time. He held the position until he retired from Tufts in 2013.
During a 55-year career as a researcher into sleep and dreams, he published more than 350 articles and 9 books and gave innumerable presentations and talks across the globe. He was the former president of the International Association for the Study of Dreams and the first editor-in-chief of its journal, Dreaming, which he helped launch. He held multiple high-level positions concurrent with his duties at Tufts, directing the Sleep and Dream Laboratory at the Boston State Hospital from 1964-1980, the Sleep Laboratory at the West-Ros-Park Mental Health Center, and the Sleep Disorders Center at Newton-Wellesley Hospital, for instance. He served as a lieutenant commander in the US Public Health Service from 1962-1964. Hartmann's interests were varied. He published as a poet and wrote articles on abortion and the effects of advertising.
Hartmann married twice, first from 1961-1974 to Barbara Snow Hengst, and again to Eva Neumann from 1995-1999. Both marriages ended in divorce. He had two children from his first marriage, Jonathan and Katherine Hartmann. He died on August 7, 2013, in Truro, MA.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of approximately 96 boxes of documents, over 100 photographs, 65 books and 129 journals, 6 digital objects, and 129 audiotapes. The collection documents the professional and personal lives of Ernest Hartmann, a preeminent sleep and dream researcher, and his parents Dr. Heinz and Dr. Dora Hartmann. Material largely dates from 1900-2013; Hartmann's working life from 1958-2013 represents the bulk of the material. The collection includes: personal and professional correspondence; research material and research data; publications, reprints, and manuscripts; audiotapes; meeting minutes and memoranda; photographs; and official and administrative paperwork.
Ernest Hartmann's papers document his more than fifty years of academic research into sleep and dreaming and the evolution of the professional organizations and journals to which he contributed. The papers relate to his research into tryptophan, adolescent mental illness, long-term effects of various drugs, vulnerability to schizophrenia, the effects of 9/11, the implications of different sleep styles and dream types, alcohol and bruxism (tooth grinding), and the development of his Boundary Questionnaire, among others. They also document his participation in numerous conferences and meetings, academic, professional, and volunteer positions; extensive correspondence with friends, romantic partners, and colleagues; poetry and interdisciplinary writings on subjects like immortality, advertising, and abortion; major life events including his marriages, children, divorces, and home sales; ephemera from his education and travels; and photographs.
In addition to Ernest Hartmann's papers, the collection contains material related to the lives and careers of Heinz and Dora Hartmann, both physicians and psychoanalysts who studied under and worked with Sigmund Freud. This material includes old family papers, manuscripts, and a selection of historical professional books (largely in German) and Austrian psychoanalytic journals. The journals – Imago, Internationale Zeitschrift für Psychoanalyse, Allgemeine Ärtzliche Zeitschrift für Psychotherapie, and Zentralblatt für Psychotherapie – date mostly from the 1930s.
Faculty research; Faculty papers; Psychology -- Research; Dreams -- Psychological aspects
- Personal papers, 1900 -- 2014; MS211.001; 10.8 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This is a temporary description based on unprocessed materials and will need to be expanded with future processing. This series can be divided roughly into four areas: alphabetical files, correspondence, dream logs, and oversized materials. The material spans Ernest Hartmann's lifetime, from family photographs to correspondence and clippings from the years just before his death.
  Alphabetical files contain professional certifications, ephemera, charts, publications, reports, syllabi, patient records, address books, sketchbooks, personal writing and diaries, correspondence, stationery, material from Eva Neumann (his second wife), official documents, and administrative paperwork.
  Correspondence from 1986-1992 was kept in folders by year and has been filed chronologically. Included in these files are personal notes, business letters, cards, and some correspondence addressed to Eva Neumann (Hartmann).
  Hartmann's personal dream logs, kept from 1984-1995, were in folders by year and have been filed chronologically.
  Oversized material consists of family photographs depicting Heinz and Dora Hartmann from their middle years to their old age and Ernest and Lawrence Hartmann as children, large unsigned watercolors, and four banners from the 1985 reunion of Massachusetts Mental Health Center psychiatric residents that Hartmann organized and attended. The material has been kept onsite in the green barcodes in box MS211.001.004. (This oversize box also contains other material from Series 2: Heinz and Dora Hartmann papers and Series 5: Research and data.)
  Arrangement
  This is a temporary description based on unprocessed materials and will need to be expanded with future processing. The original order of alphabetical files has been preserved. Correspondence has been filed chronologically. Oversized material is currently not arranged.
  Conditions Governing Access
  75 years from the date of creation. Open for research.
  - Personal papers and correspondence B-Y, letters and clippings A-C, 1900 -- 2014; MS211.001.001. (Box 1)
    75 years from the date of creation.
    File cabinet 9 Drawer 1 and 2
  - Personal papers and correspondence C-S, 1900 -- 2014; MS211.001.002. (Box 2)
    File cabinet 9 Drawer 2
  - Personal papers and correspondence, dream logs, letters, 1984 -- 1992; MS211.001.003. (Box 3)
    File Cabinet 15 Drawer 4
  - Personal papers and correspondence oversize materials, MS211.001.004 (Box 4)
    Open for research.
    This box includes materials from three different series: 001 (Personal papers and correspondence), 002 (Heinz and Dora Hartmann and family papers), and 005 (Research data and materials). This includes data sheets, posters and photographs. Also included are materials that were determined to be to fragile to go off site from the Heinz and Dora Hartmann and family papers.
    poster
  - Personal correspondence, MS211.001.097 (Box 97)
  - Correspondence, poetry, journal, and photographs, MS211.001.098 (Box 98)
- Heinz and Dora Hartmann and family papers, 1900 -- 1958; MS211.002; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This is a temporary description based on unprocessed material which will need to be expanded with future processing. This series contains the couple and family's correspondence, manuscripts, notes, publications, artwork, legal documents, and professional organization correspondence, minutes, as well as memoranda of Heinz and Dora Hartmann, ranging from 1849-1974.
  The bulk of the documents are Heinz Hartmann's correspondence (1936-1957) relating to the International Psychoanalytic Association (IPA). IPA-related material covers such areas as the Freud Centenary Celebrations, engagement with national psychoanalytic societies, and his work on behalf of IPA during the "French Schism," in which members of the Psychoanalytic Society of Paris (Jaques Lacan, Daniel Lagache, Favez-Boutonier, Dolto, and Revershon-Jouve) split to form the French Psychoanalytic Society on June 16th, 1953.
  Professional correspondence might also include work with the New York Psychoanalytic Society and Institute in which Heinz and Dora were both active members. Also included are birthday cards and poems made by Ernest and Lawrence for their mother Dora Hartmann, the Hartmann's immigration documents, and other legal documents. These materials are mostly in German as well as English, and in French.
  Material was not arranged. Future arrangement could be by date.
  - Heinz and Dora, IPA, letters and manuscripts, 1948 -- 1958; MS211.002.005. (Box 5)
    Box 4 and Box 5
  - Heinz and Dora, IPA, family documents, 1900 -- 1956; MS211.002.006. (Box 6)
    Box 5
- Professional correspondence and professional associations, 1963 -- 2013; MS211.003; 12.0 Linear Feet
  This is a temporary description based on unprocessed material and will need to be expanded with future processing. This series includes minutes of professional meetings, brochures, papers, journals, and correspondence ranging from 1967-2013. Within this series are three distinct groupings according to the way Ernest Hartmann arranged this material: (1) professional correspondence, (2) Association for the Study of Dreaming (ASD) material, and (3) involvement in other professional associations and conferences.
  (1) The professional correspondence (1967-2012) includes letters from colleagues and researchers, professional organizations, publishers, and the public.
  (2) ASD materials (1987-2013) include correspondence, meeting minutes, reports, conference materials, and newsletters. The bulk of the material is from 1987-1998.
  (3) Other professional organizations with which Ernest Hartmann was involved and are represented in this collection include the Associated Professional Sleep Society (APSS), Boston Psychoanalytic Society and Institute (BPSI), World Knowledge Dialogue (WKD), International Society for Tryptophan Research (ISTRY), and the American Society of Neuropsychotherapy (ACNP). Material relating to these organizations includes correspondence, meeting notes, and conference papers. Personal letters and cards may be included.
  This series contains material in English, some material is in French and German.
  These are proposed ideas for arrangement and may change based on further processing. The current arrangement reflects the three main content areas: personal correspondence, ASD materials, and professional involvement.
  Material was rehoused with minimal processing. Further refinement can be done to organize materials by date. Originally we planned to create two series: one for professional correspondence and professional organization material, and conference talks and material in another. However, it became clear that there was a great deal of overlap so we decided to merge the series. Dividers were placed between the correspondence, ASD material, and conference material indicating the start and end of each section so it is still possible to rearrange this material in the future.
  Additionally, material in box MS211.008.089 may be affiliated with this series. These may be connected to the ASD materials because they were located in the same filing cabinet (file cabinet 2) as some of the ASD material but were not labeled as such. The material in box MS211.008.089 came originally from drawers 3 and 4 and because it contained reprints, unpublished materials, and PhD theses, published materials were weeded and all unpublished materials kept. It is unclear whether these materials were connected to Hartmann's role as editor of Dreaming. (See the Processing Notes for more explanation).
  - Professional corresondence and involvement, 1967 -- 1975; MS211.003.007. (Box 7)
    File Cabinet 6 Drawer 2
  - Professional corresondence and involvement, 1978 -- 1992; MS211.003.008. (Box 8)
    File Cabinet 6 Drawer11, File Cabinet I [2nd floor] Drawer 2
  - Professional corresondence and involvement, 1977 -- 1981; MS211.003.009. (Box 9)
    File Cabinet 3 Drawer 1
  - Professional corresondence and involvement, 1972 -- 2012; MS211.003.010. (Box 10)
    File Cabinet 3 Drawer, File Cabinet I [2nd floor]Drawer 2
  - Professional correspondence and involvement, ASD, 1987 -- 1992; MS211.003.011. (Box 11)
    File Cabinet 3 Drawer 2, File Cabinet 2 Drawer1
  - Professional correspondence and involvement, ASD, 1993 -- 1998; MS211.003.012. (Box 12)
    File Cabinet 3 Drawer 2, File Cabinet 2 Drawer 1
  - Professional correspondence and involvement, ASD, dreaming, applications, 1963 -- 2013; MS211.003.013. (Box 13)
    File Cabinet 2 Drawer 1, File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer 1
  - Professional correspondence and involvement, applications and old meetings, 1967 -- 1982; MS211.003.014. (Box 14)
    Box 11, File Cabinet 5 Drawer 3
  - Professional correspondence and involvement, old meetings and talks, 1986 -- 2010; MS211.003.015. (Box 15)
    File Cabinet 5 Drawer 3, File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer 1
  - Professional correspondence and involvement, employment files, 1999 -- 2002; MS211.003.016. (Box 16)
    File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer1
- Scientific publications and drafts, 1958 -- 2003; MS211.004; 16.8 Linear Feet
  This is a temporary description based on unprocessed materials and will need to be expanded with future processing. This series covers the period from 1958-2003 and contains research articles and drafts of Ernest Hartmann's articles, books, and encyclopedia entries.
  Hartmann began publishing early in his career, building on his own research on sleep and dreams and collaborating with scientists all over the world. Articles based on Hartmann's study data as well as data from other researchers' studies.
  Hartmann had two websites to showcase his academic works: http://ernesthartmann.org/ERNEST_HARTMANN_MD/HOME.html and href="http://www.tufts.edu/~ehartm01/ [accessed on August 5 2014). Each website contains links to downloadable documents such as his Boundary Questionnaire and recent talks and papers. There is extensive overlap between the materials on each site. The sites were crawled using ArchiveIt on August 5, 2014, and have not yet been made available. They are also available through the Internet Archive.
  This is a temporary description based on unprocessed materials and will need to be expanded with future processing. This series was created by interleaving two blocks of research material, each filed differently. Originally, Hartmann had organized these two sets of records in two ways: (1) reprints were each assigned a sequential number and filed accordingly; (2) article drafts containing correspondence and research data were originally filed chronologically or by larger subject matter. The order created by pre-processers follows the chronological/sequential order of a bibliography Hartmann created of his published works from 1959-2011. Undated material has been filed at the end of this series.
  - Publications and drafts, 1958 -- 1966; MS211.004.017. (Box 17)
    File Cabinet 12 Drawer 1and 2, File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer 1
  - Publications and drafts, 1966 -- 1967; MS211.004.018. (Box 18)
    File Cabinet 12 Drawer 1, File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer 1
  - Publications and drafts, 1967 -- 1969; MS211.004.019. (Box 19)
  - Publications and drafts, 1969 -- 1972; MS211.004.020 (Box 20)
    File Cabinet 12 Drawer 1 and 2, File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer 1
  - Publications and drafts, 1972 -- 1973; MS211.004.021 (Box 21)
    File Cabinet 12 Drawer 2, File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer 1
  - Publications and drafts, 1973; MS211.004.022. (Box 22)
    File Cabinet 12 Drawer 2 and 3, File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer 1
  - Publications and drafts, 1973 -- 1975; MS211.004.023 (Box 23)
  - Publications and drafts, 1975 -- 1976; MS211.004.024 (Box 24)
    File Cabinet 12 Drawer 3 and 4
  - Publications and drafts, 1976; MS211.004.025 (Box 25)
    File Cabinet 12 Drawer 3, File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer 1
  - Publications and drafts, 1976 -- 1979; MS211.004.026 (Box 26)
    File Cabinet 12 Drawer 4
  - Publications and drafts, 1977 -- 1979; MS211.004.027 (Box 27)
    File Cabinet 8 Drawer 1, File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer 1
  - Publications and drafts, 1979 -- 1981; MS211.004.028. (Box 28)
    File Cabinet 8 Drawer1, File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer 1
  - Publications and drafts, 1981 -- 1997; MS211.004.029 (Box 29)
    File Cabinet 8 Drawer 2, File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer 1
  - Publications and drafts, 1995 -- 2003; MS211.004.030 (Box 30)
    File cabinet 11 Drawer 3, File Cabinet 12 Drawer 1, 2, and 3, File Cabinet II [2nd floor] Drawer 2
- Research data and materials, 1900 -- 2014; MS211.005; 67.2 Linear Feet
  This is a temporary description based on unprocessed materials and will need to be expanded with future processing. This series contains research data, qualitative and quantitative datasets, human subject files, grant materials, study-related correspondence, and unpublished study material, spanning the length of Ernest Hartmann's long research career. Currently some dissertations are interfiled with studies, reflecting the order in which they were found; these may need to be moved or weeded. Patient test score sheets in box MS211.005.034 were found to be moldy; the material was photocopied and the originals were destroyed.
  Major research projects included in this series are as follows: Vulnerability to Schizophrenia; Nightmares; Contextualizing Images; studies related to tryptophan and other drugs effects; Boundary Questionnaire; Long and Short Sleepers; Alcohol and Bruxism (tooth-grinding); and 9/11 study. An attempt was made to keep together material related to major studies; box labels note the titles of major studies.
  Hartmann's research into the effects of the amino acid tryptophan lasted from 1966 to 1991, when it was banned for a time in the U.S., and the amount of associated material is correspondingly large. Hartmann was a major proponent of using tryptophan as a drug to treat insomnia and other sleep disorders without unpleasant side effects. During the 1980s Hartmann worked with the Thompson Medical Company on clinical trials for FDA approval of a tryptophan-based drug. Government publications on FDA drug approval dating from 1966-1980 and research publications on the effects of tryptophan have been weeded from these files.
  The material on Vulnerability to Schizophrenia spans the years 1982-1987. Hartmann's early research into adolescents in mental institutions led him to consider that certain personality traits and reactions to stress could predict later incidence of schizophrenia. He initially used the records of adolescent patients at the MMHC, then data gathered by Sheldon and Eleanor Glueck in the 1940s/50s in their studies on juvenile delinquency and data from adolescents treated at what was then called the Judge Baker Guidance Center. A letter Hartmann wrote explaining the course of his research and the dates during which each research project was active has been copied and placed at the start of the Vulnerability to Schizophrenia material in box MS211.005.054 as well as in the collection documentation folder.
  Hartmann's interest in the relationship between sleep characteristics and personality traits led to a deeper investigation of the link between nightmares and temperament. Material related to nightmare studies dates from 1976-1986, though Hartmann continued writing on nightmares for years afterward. This series contains data, subject files, scoresheets, and correspondence related to his 1984 book The Nightmare: The Psychology and Biology of Terrifying Dreams.
  Hartmann' research material on 'boundaries' spans from 1985-2000. The Boundary Questionnaire (BQ), one of Hartmann's most well-known creations, derived from his research on the personalities of nightmare sufferers. The BQ was a personality questionnaire that measured the subject's "thick" or "thin" boundaries. Hartmann's research led eventually to the 1992 publication of a book, Boundaries in the Mind: A New Psychology of Personality. This series contains data from his boundary research as well as drafts of and correspondence related to his book.
  Five floppy disks found in this series have been digitized (see note below). The physical location of the disks at the time of rehousing have been flagged, i.e. markers and separations sheets have been added to the physical files.
  Disks found in MS211.005.063: